בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, today's דף daf is today's דף
daf is דף ח, daf Chet, and we pick up in the
middle of a גמרא Gemara discussing the parameters of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael for the purposes of גיטין, Gittin, and an interesting discussion about
whether if somebody brings in a on the water in Israel, we're
assuming now it means a river in Israel, whether it's like bringing
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's literal actually said on boat, so
we're assuming it's a boat on a river in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael like bringing in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. And what's that debate
about? So the גמרא Gemara yesterday ties the debate between a debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים Chachamim about if you
have dirt on a boat and it's growing crops on the boat,
whether the crops are obligated in תרומות Terumos and מעשרות. Ma'asros. And
the boat is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where חכמים Chachamim say
it is and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says only when the boat
is scraping against the bottom of the river and the river floor
and then also the גמרא Gemara compared it to
an
עציץ, atzitz, a planter, a flower pot with
a hole in it. So רש"י Rashi says that it's a pottery
boat. I don't know how well a pottery boat will float. תוספות
Tosefos says that it's a wooden boat, that a wooden boat is
considered to be porous. Anyway, but the point is not whether the
boat is what makes it considered like a flower pot with a
hole. The question is why is that at
all relevant to saying בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, Befanecha Nichtav U'befanecha Nechtam,
which has to do with other considerations. So it seems clear that
this גמרא Gemara is using like a pre-packaged definition of the land
of Israel and not focusing on whether the actual practical considerations are
present or not present to the point that to determine whether you
say בפני נכתב Befanecha Nichtav is a function of whether crops growing
would be obligated in תרומות Terumos and מעשרות. Ma'asros. Although תוספות Tosefos
points out that how far are we going to take this. Like
תוספות Tosefos says does that mean that if you give a גט
get in an attic on a second floor in Israel that you
don't say בפני נכתב Befanecha Nichtav because if you have dirt on
a second floor and it's not connected to the dirt on the
ground it wouldn't be חייב chayav in תרומות Terumos and מעשרות? Ma'asros?
So well no at least there the dirt underneath you is חייב
chayav in תרומות Terumos and מעשרות Ma'asros but here if you're in
the river maybe nothing would be חייב. chayav. Anyway it gets a
little strange. So take a look at the תוספות, Tosefos, let's just
pick up with this. We didn't get a full opportunity to explain
this.
Soil under the water, right?
Well yes, but תוספות Tosefos is assuming saying that he's assuming that
the soil under the water would not be obligated but it's still
not fully answering anyway תוספות Tosefos has a nice answer or explanation
he says like this.
So it says תוספות עציץ Tosefos Atzitz but read from one, two,
three, six lines from the bottom of the דף daf on ז
עמוד ב Zayin Amud Bet and תוספות Tosefos says the following: דנהי
דהכא דאינה גוששת לרבי יהודה מדהוה ליה חוץ לארץ לענין מעשר חשיבנא
חוץ לארץ לענין גט. de'nehei de'hacha de'eina gosheses le'Rabbi Yehuda mi'de'hava lei
Chutz La'aretz le'inyan ma'aser chashivnan Chutz La'aretz le'inyan get. It's like four
words into the line. He
says if it's not scraping on the bottom of the ground for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda since it's a חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz for
מעשר ma'aser stuff that grows in it would not be obligated in
מעשר ma'aser you would it would be considered חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
for גט get purposes now what's the logic there? So תוספות Tosefos
says to you: הני משום כיון דשם חוץ לארץ על המקום hani
mishum keivan desheim Chutz La'aretz al hamakom since that place is considered
not in the land of Israel צריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
ואף על גב דשמיכי וגמירי כדי שלא תחלוק ממדינת הים. tzarich lomar
befanecha nichtav ubefanecha nechtam ve'af al gav deshmichi u'gemiri kedei shelo tachalok
midinas hayam.
Says there's a lot like packed in that תוספות Tosefos but he
says it's true they know the גט get can easily get עדים
edim to come from a boat right they're right there in the
land they just step off the boat and people know the הלכות
halachos of לשמה. lishmah. So תוספות Tosefos says from a practical standpoint
תוספות Tosefos says there should be no need to say לשמה. lishmah.
But כדי שלא תחלוק ממדינת הים kedei shelo tachalok midinas hayam from
a formalistic perspective this is labeled as חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz okay?
So תוספות Tosefos is saying look it's true the practical aspects is
not what is guiding us here in terms of this issue of
the boat. From a practical perspective you should not have to say
בפני נכתב. Befanecha Nichtav. But from a formalistic perspective רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is saying that if you're on a boat in the land
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you're not considered to be in the
land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael so I don't care if the
practical considerations are satisfied
from formalistically you're in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and the evidence of
that is that stuff that would grow would be exempt in תרומות
Terumos and מעשרות Ma'asros that's not a technical תרומות Terumos and מעשרות
Ma'asros point that's a question about formally is it considered to be
in the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and since formally it
is not you're in the air space or the water space of
the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael but you're not in the
land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that he said would obligate you
to say בפני נכתב. Befanecha Nichtav. And then he says אבל בגוששת
aval be'goshes but if it's scraping on the bottom of... of the
riverbed. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or רבנן אפילו בשאינו גוששת, Rabanan afilu
beshe'eino gosheshet, the rabbis even if it's not scraping on the bottom,
it's just in a boat in a river, כיוון דשמה ארץ ישראל
על המקום, keivan deshma Eretz Yisrael al hamakom, since the place is
labeled ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the evidence being that you bring תרומות
ומעשרות, Terumot uMa'aserot, okay, אף על פי דמחסוס כלי אין לו חבל
בנעשה. af al pi demachsus kli ein lo chevel bena'aseh. Now תוספות
Tosafot says even if, right, תוספות Tosafot is dealing with this idea,
does the boat have to be porous? What, you only say, don't
say בפני נכתב befanai nichtav if you're on a porous boat? תוספות
Tosafot says no, I don't care for that because the dirt isn't
connected, you're exempt. That's a technical תרומות ומעשרות Terumot uMa'aserot issue, that
the dirt is, you know, it's not porous, so the dirt isn't
connected, but the point is, were it porous, it would be considered
like the dirt was connected, so the real bigger issue here is
you're considered in the land of Israel. For the rabbis when you're
on a boat, you're considered in the land of Israel, and any
dirt and anything that grows is growing in the land of Israel,
and for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, when it's scraping on the bottom,
you're considered in the land of Israel. Now, that might be that
for the dirt to be connected, you need a porous boat, but
before that, fundamentally you're considered in the land if it's scraping on
the bottom. So in that case,
בשור כך לא יחשב כחוץ לארץ, bishur kach lo yeichashev kechutz la'aretz,
so if there's just a dirt problem, that's not the issue. So
what תוספות Tosafot says is, for something to be חייב chayav in
תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot uMa'aserot, you need two criteria reached. You need to
say that the stuff is growing in the land of Israel, and
you need to say that the dirt is connected to the ground.
For בפני נכתב, befanai nichtav, who cares about the dirt? Okay, that's
a technical תרומות ומעשרות Terumot uMa'aserot issue. But what we can do
is look at that הלכה halacha to say are you considered in
the land of Israel or out of the land of Israel. And
תוספות Tosafot makes clear is, obviously this is not the pragmatic concerns
of do they יודעי לשמה מצויים לקיים, yodei lishmah metzuyim lekayem, it's
a purely formalistic definition. So if from a formalistic תרומות ומעשרות Terumot
uMa'aserot perspective you say in the river on a boat in a
river you're not in Israel, the same would be true about בפני
נכתב. befanai nichtav. If you say you are in Israel, then that
would be true about בפני נכתב. befanai nichtav. So this גמרא, Gemara,
you know, is not looking at redefining the criteria based on the
specific needs of בפני נכתב. befanai nichtav. It's saying let's look at
a pre-packaged definition from תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot uMa'aserot, and we will take
that and apply that here whether לקולא lekula or לחומרא, lechumra, whether
to have to say or to not have to say. And that's
very much again against the simple sense we get from our משנה
Mishna that draws the borders of Israel and עכו Akko and all
those places based on the specific considerations of בפני נכתב befanai nichtav
and not based on the standard border for other areas of the
הלכה halacha of land of Israel.
It's purely formalistic. Yeah. And most of the time when I'm on
a boat in the river at this spot, it would not be
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Right. In the year where there's a
drought, the boat is still touching the bottom, it still should not
be in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
I don't know what to say about that, but anyway, theoretic, maybe
you can make that argument. Yeah, although right, anyway. So let's go
back now to the גמרא. Gemara. But that's the point, this גמרא
Gemara is clearly drawing on laws of תרומות ומעשרות Terumot uMa'aserot to
define the parameters of Israel for בפני נכתב. befanai nichtav. So this
גמרא Gemara clearly is going on formalistic pre-packaged definitions and not on
defining a unique set of criteria that is relevant for בפני נכתב.
befanai nichtav. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues on ח עמוד
א. chet amud aleph. Okay,
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, we are five lines down from the top
of the page, and again we're trying to discuss this issue about
a debate of whether you have to say it if you're on
a boat.
So רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, somebody could write a Dr. Seuss book
about this exactly, would you say it on a boat? Would you
say it on
a... anyway. Oh my god, that is such a perfect פורים שפיל
Purim Shpiel we should do. All right, anyway.
A
thousand people just heard that.
Right, I understand. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר בנהרות ארץ ישראל כולי
עלמא לא פליגי. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar benaharot Eretz Yisrael kuli
alma lo pligi. If it's in a river, nobody disagrees. Like, that's
within the borders of Israel. Whatever you say about תרומות ומעשרות Terumot
uMa'aserot and maybe that is more related to dirt issues, anyway, that's
clearly in the borders of Israel, presumably. I mean he doesn't say
which way לא פליגי, lo pligi, but presumably רש"י Rashi does say.
Look at רש"י, Rashi, four lines down from the top. כולי עלמא
לא פליגי דארץ ישראל נינהו. kuli alma lo pligi de'Eretz Yisrael ninhu.
ואף על גב דאין ספינה גוששת, ve'af al gav de'ein sfina gosheshet,
even if it's not scraping the bottom. דטעמא דגט לאו משום יניקה
מן הקרקע הוא, deta'ama deget lav mishum yanika min hakarka hu, it's
not about the dirt issue and is the dirt connected to the
dirt of Israel, כמעשר ושביעית, kema'aser ushvi'it, that's not what it's based
on. הלכך לא שנא נהר
ולא שנא יבשה. hilkach lo shna nahar velo shna yabasha. So therefore,
רש"י Rashi says it doesn't make. So here saying, that's all תרומות
ומעשרות Terumot uMa'aserot issue. Everybody agrees if you're in a river, you're
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so what's the debate if you're
in a boat? אלא כי פליגי, ela ki pligi, back to the
גמרא, Gemara, what's the debate? בים הגדול, beyam hagadol, you're in the
Mediterranean. Ah, so if you're in the Mediterranean, then we have a
real question off the shore of Israel. Then we have a real
question, is that international waters? At what stage is something in the
Mediterranean considered to be in the land of Israel or not?
Okay, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. איזהו ארץ ישראל
ואיזהו חוצה לארץ. eizehu Eretz Yisrael ve'eizehu Chutza la'Aretz. We're still going
to use pre-packaged definitions, but not the question of the river. The
river in the Israel clearly you're in the land. Any debate about
that is a debate about is it connected to the dirt. Dirt
is not an interesting question for בפני נחתם. Bifnei Nechtam. But we're
still going to use a pre-packaged definition, a formalistic definition from תרומות
ומעשרות, Terumot u'Ma'asrot, but of something that's much more fundamentally a debate
of is it part of Israel or not part of Israel for
תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot. What is that debate? In the Mediterranean. איזהו
ארץ ואיזהו חוץ לארץ? Eizehu Eretz v'eizehu Chutz La'aretz? What's considered part
of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, what's חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz for the
land of תרומות? Terumot? For the law of תרומות? Terumot? כל ששופע
ויורד מטורי אמנון ולפנים ארץ ישראל. Kol she'shofei'a v'yored mi'Turei Amnon v'lifnim
Eretz Yisrael.
Anything that slopes from טורי אמנון Turei Amnon inward is Israel. מטורי
אמנון ולחוץ חוץ לארץ. Mi'Turei Amnon v'lachutz Chutz La'aretz. From טורי אמנון
Turei Amnon and to the out is חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Now
טורי אמנון, Turei Amnon, רש"י Rashi says is the Aramaic of הור
ההר. Hor HaHar. Right? And הור ההר Hor HaHar is...
if you've got basically...
my hand is now an eraser. Okay, anyway. Alright, so you basically
have, anyway, okay, you've got... boy you have to excuse my, oh
I don't know what I just did there. You have to excuse
my artistic, my lack of artistic skills. Anyway.
Do you have tissues?
If you... oh okay you got tissues. Alright, anyway, something like this.
This is the ים הגדול. Yam HaGadol. Okay. So the משנה Mishnah
says, the תורה Torah says that the borders of the land of
Israel from the west are the ים הגדול Yam HaGadol and it
says from the ים הגדול Yam HaGadol תתאו לכם הור ההר tita'u
lachem Hor HaHar that the next point, right, what's sort of going
like here's like here's נחל מצרים, Nachal Mitzrayim, which as I think,
what do they say that is, Wadi el Arish or something?
Anyway, okay, נחל מצרים Nachal Mitzrayim it says sort of like is
as it's drawing the borders of Israel and then it goes sort
of that's like in the south and going all the way up
to ים הגדול, Yam HaGadol, and then it says the ים הגדול
Yam HaGadol is the... is the western border and then it says
you go to הור ההר. Hor HaHar. Okay, which is somewhere here.
Okay.
Where אהרן Aharon died? Yeah, הור ההר. Hor HaHar.
Yeah, I mean, I don't know if it's the same הור ההר
Hor HaHar because אהרן Aharon obviously died somewhere over there. Yeah, I
know, but it's some different הור ההר Hor HaHar I think. Anyway,
okay. So that's רש"י Rashi says that the Aramaic of that is
טורי אמנון. Turei Amnon. Okay, טורי אמנון. Turei Amnon. So, anyway, so
this is considered to be... so רש"י Rashi says anything that slopes
away, which for רש"י Rashi means north, is חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
and anything that slopes from, if you imagine a mountain ridge, right,
you imagine the ridge, a mountain ridge, it slopes down like that,
anything that slopes south is ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, mountain ridge.
So therefore that's הור ההר. Hor HaHar. Alright. So it says, כל
ששופע ויורד מטורי אמנון ולפנים ארץ ישראל מטורי אמנון ולחוץ חוץ לארץ.
Kol she'shofei'a v'yored mi'Turei Amnon v'lifnim Eretz Yisrael mi'Turei Amnon v'lachutz Chutz
La'aretz.
נסין שבים? Nasin she'ba'yam? How about islands? Now are there any islands
off of the Mediterranean near Israel?
Are there any? I don't think there are any. Anyway, theoretically if
there were, little maybe it's just tiny little, you know, tiny little
like a, you know, piece like whatever, you know, just little pieces
of land, right, tiny little whatever they are. So if there are
some things that are off the coast, נסין שבים, nasin she'ba'yam, רואים
אותן כאילו חוט מתוח עליהן מטורי אמנון עד נחל מצרים.
ro'in otan k'ilu chut matuach aleihen mi'Turei
Amnon ad Nachal Mitzrayim.
You basically draw a string from טורי אמנון Turei Amnon to נחל
מצרים, Nachal Mitzrayim, which is the, which is the... the border here
at the bottom of the... of the Mediterranean, okay? So the border
of Israel goes up to this point in the Mediterranean, then you've
got the Mediterranean and then it picks up over here. So basically
you draw a string from הור ההר Hor HaHar to נחל מצרים,
Nachal Mitzrayim, which is this border of Israel, and anything that is
in between this string and the coast is considered to be Israel
waters, and everything that's further out is international waters. Okay, and that's
for the הלכות halachot of תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot. Now that is
where actually you would want to borrow a definition, right? You would
say, okay, we've got this idea of בפני נחתם, Bifnei Nechtam, do
they know לשמה, lishmah, but how about do we just look at,
you know, how do we look at the at the waters? Is
the Mediterranean, is that part of, is it connected or not connected?
So let's look at this definition for תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot that
it says everything between this line is considered connected to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. So we'll use the same definition for בפני נחתם. Bifnei
Nechtam. Okay. נסין שבים רואים אותן כאילו חוט מתוח עליהן מטורי אמנון
עד נחל מצרים מן החוט ולפנים ארץ ישראל מן החוט ולחוץ חוץ
לארץ. Nasin she'ba'yam ro'in otan k'ilu chut matuach aleihen mi'Turei Amnon ad
Nachal Mitzrayim, min hachut v'lifnim Eretz Yisrael, min hachut v'lachutz Chutz La'aretz.
Okay,
that's the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma position. So therefore if you have
something brought on a boat and the boat is within Israel waters,
you would not say בפני נחתם. Bifnei Nechtam. רבי יהודה אומר כל
שכנגד ארץ ישראל הרי הוא כארץ ישראל. Rabbi Yehudah omer: Kol she'keneged
Eretz Yisrael harei hu k'Eretz Yisrael.
Anything opposite Israel counts as Israel. שנאמר וגבול ים והיה לכם הים
הגדול וגבול. Shene'emar: u'gvul yam v'hayah lachem haYam HaGadol u'gvul. And the
border of the ocean, and the ocean shall be for you the
border. Now it's a little redundant. So he says the purpose of
the... redundancy is to give you more of the Mediterranean that is
connected to Israel. Okay, והנסים
שבצדדין vehanissim shebatzidadin now the islands off on the sides, אומרים כאילו
חוט מתוח עליהם omrim ke'ilu chut matuach aleihem you take a string
מכפלוריא ועד ים אוקיינוס miKaflurya ve'ad Yam Okeinos
from Kaflurya which is a little funny white you know Rashi says
essentially it's טורי אמנון Turei Amnon so why it's using a different
term is not clear. Anyway, but from this טורי אמנון Turei Amnon
to the Atlantic, ומנחל מצרים עד ים אוקיינוס uminachal Mitzrayim ad Yam
Okeinos and from the Nachal Mitzrayim to the Atlantic, מהחוט ולפנים ארץ
ישראל mehachut ulefanim Eretz Yisrael within
between those two strings is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, מהחוט ולחוץ חוצה
לארץ mehachut ulechutz chutz la'aretz outside of them is חוצה לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. So what he says is no, no, no, you don't just
do this. What you do is you do this.
Okay, so for him, where, oh thank you. Did they really do
anything about that? Yeah, after the
fact.
I mean for him you go throughout the Mediterranean.
Okay, so for him you
go like this.
Okay, and anything basically opposite Israel is any you know belongs to
Israel for תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'aserot. Okay, and anything at the outside,
so I don't know, here's the Mediterranean, okay this will just show
my ignorance in terms of where is like what do you got
here? You got France here or something? Spain I mean. Spain, right.
Where's what? Morocco? Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we go to Gibraltar.
Spain extends into what?
It basically extends until its land although they thought the Atlantic was
the end of the world so until it hits the edge of
the world but anyway but extends until its land. Hold on.
Let me take a look at a map. I was going to
say it's going to hit Italy, right?
Hold on, I'm looking at a picture. Okay, here we go. I'll
try to draw you thanks oh my God, okay, whoa. All right,
it's pretty huge there.
Oh my God, hold on.
Okay, wait, wait, so
Spain is like, yeah, what do we have here?
We've
got here's Greece coming out here, right, and then you've got here
you got Italy, okay.
And then it is going to hit land. And then it's going
to get France, right, and then it'll get Spain and then we're
on the
higher I mean
and then that'll be the African coast or something like that.
Anyway, that's my gorgeous drawing.
Anyway,
so for him, well I don't know, actually Italy and whatnot is
higher than Israel, those are much higher. They're part of Greater Israel.
Those are yeah anyway so basically actually that's much higher than Israel
anyway but anyway all of that basically would be anything now. The
question is so basically it would get you it would so presumably
it's only the islands not the actual land masses. Okay, so it
would get you like Sicily, right? Cyprus. Right.
And anyway Greece maybe? I don't know. Anyway, all of that would
belong to Israel.
On רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehudah's map because Israel's bigger than China.
I know, I know, it's totally out of proportion. Anyway, all right,
so exactly. Everybody'll everybody right, okay. Anyway,
so for him, all right, so the question about whether the question
about whether a boat is considered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or חוצה
לארץ chutz la'aretz is what happens if it's here? Everybody agrees that
a boat is in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. If it's way out
here in the Mediterranean, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah would say it is
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and the חכמים Chachamim would say it's considered
to be חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. So again we're borrowing from תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u'ma'aserot but we're borrowing something which is a more reasonable
debate, not something that relates to the dirt, but what part of
the waters are considered connected to the actual country itself.
So in terms of the islands in that concept like Sicily would
be part of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Right, at least חייב בתרומות ומעשרות. chayav b'terumot u'ma'aserot. Now I want
to read a תוספות Tosafot about this which is because it's a
little funny. Anyway, it says like this.
Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבנן האי
וגבול מאי עבדי ליה? Rabbanan hai u'gevul mai avdi leh? What do
they do with the word וגבול u'gevul which רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah
says to use to include more like mostly the Mediterranean for these
הלכות halachot for as part of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael like draw
these parallel lines not this connecting line not a diagonal line. So
what do they do with it? מיבעי ליה לנסים, mibai leh lenissim,
they need it to tell you that the islands are included but
not to tell you that you draw these parallel lines, only that
you draw from the northernmost part to the southernmost part and you
connect the two dots. רבי יהודה נסים לא צריכי קרא, Rebbi Yehudah
nissim lo tzrichi kra, no you don't need a פסוק, pasuk, ים
yam tells you that the ocean is part of the land, it
means you get the islands, so the extra וגבול u'gevul tells you
you draw these parallel lines. Now let's take a look at a
cute little תוספות Tosafot here which is רבי יהודה אומר כל שכנגד
ארץ ישראל. Rebbi Yehudah omer kol shekeneged Eretz Yisrael. So תוספות Tosafot
says, שאל רבינו פטר את רבינו תם sha'al Rabbeinu Peter et Rabbeinu
Tam דבזמן הזה היה לו להתחייב לרבי יהודה במעשר שאנו במערבה של
ארץ ישראל. debizman hazeh haya lo lehitchayev leRebbi Yehudah b'ma'aser she'anu b'maarava
shel Eretz Yisrael. You know we should be obligated in תרומה ומעשר
Terumah u'Ma'aser according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here where we are
in like France, because we're opposite, we're to the east or to
the west of Israel. Now it is actually west and north, I
don't think it would fall between the two parallel lines.
But France is on the Mediterranean.
Yeah, but is it between the two parallel lines of Israel? Like
I drew totally out of proportion, right? Spain's the only thing that.
I mean you know whatever. I mean it's like way right I
mean the islands the stuff starts up here, right? Yeah. Right. Okay,
like that whatever. I mean that's sort of what it looks like.
So you really wouldn't get I don't know what you get what
you would actually get that falls between the lines. Anyway, but תוספות
Tosfos still wants to know really how far you're gonna take this.
Like is this a question? You know is Spain considered part of
ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Okay. והשיב Ve'heshiv and he responded דלא קיימא
לן כרבי יהודה. delo kaima lan k'Rabbi Yehuda. All right we don't
פסקן pasken that way. אבל קשיא, Aval kasha, וכי רבי יהודה המכיר
בכל ארץ ישראל עד קונס שכולם היו בקיאין לשמה שאינם צריכים לקיים,
vechi Rabbi Yehuda hamakir bechol Eretz Yisrael ad Kunas shekulam hayu bekiyim
lishma she'einam tzrichim lekaymo, so now we have to also ask the
question, right? What does this have to do with גיטין Gittin purposes?
Okay, it's all very nice that you're חייב chayav in תרומות Trumos
and מעשרות, Ma'asros,
but does that mean that they all knew about the laws of
לשמה? lishma? There was travel? Again, what that shows is that this
גמרא Gemara is dealing with just prepackaged definitions, you know, it's not
dealing with the things that are really connected to the תקנה. takana.
And then he says ואין צריך לומר בפני נכתב לכך יש לומר
דלא כבשו הכל עד בבל. ve'ein tzarich lomar befanai nechtav lekach yeshomar
delo kivshu hachol ad Bavel. No,
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda means is were you to conquer that
land you'd be חייב chayav in
תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Ma'asros because that would become part of Israel
because it's between the border the borders. But if it wasn't conquered
it's not part of Israel. So therefore practically none of this really
applies whether to תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Ma'asros or whether to say
בפני נכתב befanai nechtav because it was never really conquered. Okay, that's
answer number one. אינמי Inami כפירוש בקונטרס דכל שכנגד ארץ ישראל היינו
כל הים שכנגד ארץ ישראל. k'pirush b'Kuntres dechol shekeneged Eretz Yisrael haynu
kol hayam shekeneged Eretz Yisrael.
He doesn't mean all land masses opposite Israel are שייך shayach to
Israel. דלא הוי ביבשה עד קונס אלא בנסים שבים הגדול דוקא. delo
havay beyabasha ad Kunas ela banasim shebaYam HaGadol davka. No,
no, no, we're only talking about islands in the Mediterranean. We're not
talking about major land masses, okay. So you would get you know
you'd get Sicily maybe and something in Greece, that you would get.
But you know a major land masses you wouldn't get. דוקא Davka
כדכתיב עד הים הגדול מבוא השמש יהיה גבולכם וכתיב ושתי גבולך מים
סוף ועד ים פלשתים וממדבר הנהר פירוש ים סוף מצד אדום k'dichtiv
ad HaYam HaGadol mevo hashemesh yiheye gevulchem uchtiv veshatati gevulcha miYam Suf
ve'ad Yam Pelishtim umiMidbar hanahar pirush Yam Suf mitzad Adom etc., etc.,
etc. Okay, עוד יש לומר od yesh lomar
the last thing he says is שיודע היה דבקיאין לשמה ופשוט יודע
היה למן היכן ישראל עומדים sheyodeia haya d'bekiyim lishma u'pishat yodeia laman
hichan Yisrael omdim where he knew that everybody that any place where
Jews within that range actually did know לשמה. lishma. So the interesting
thing is that the first and the last answer besides the question
if France is חייב chayav in תרומות Trumos and מעשרות, Ma'asros, the
first and the last answer basically is going back to how is
this addressing practical concerns about לשמה lishma or אינם בקיאים לקיימו. einam
bekiyim lekaymo. And he's like well, he happened to know that those
concerns were being addressed. But the but the middle answer is the
more interesting one, it's also more of the פשט pshat of the
גמרא, Gemara, that we're not talking about major land masses we're only
talking about islands. And that answers basically saying well a it solves
if France isn't חייב chayav in תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Ma'asros because
it's not a little island in the in the Mediterranean. But what
it also says is it doesn't really matter if the לשמה lishma
issues are being addressed, there's certain formal definitions. Once you define what
Israel is, islands off of the Israeli of the coast of Israel
are considered part of Israel whether those whether those criteria are or
not being met. Right so again just showing you know that it's
really not according to this גמרא Gemara based on the question about
are we really addressing the needs of the תקנה, takana, it's let's
just use a definition of the land of Israel that we have
elsewhere and at least for this question about what's the status about
the islands off of the coast, yes.
I have a simple non-conceptual question. Is this Rabbi Peter, is that
his name?
No, I don't know, פטר Patar I think. I don't know פטר.
Patar. Anyway, what about validating the signatures though?
Yeah,
I mean that's the funny thing is that we would sort of
say like sometimes you follow a תקנה takana even though it doesn't
match perfectly with the needs, you know.
And that's like we were saying before about the stuff in the
the boats in the river, you know. Although this is a little
bit more bizarre because the boats in the river you could say
we don't have to maybe we wouldn't have to, but anyway, the
point is that's what you get when you try to use a
definition that exists elsewhere it's not going to exactly match and תוספות
Tosfos is trying to make it work, but the simple sense of
this גמרא Gemara is no, you know, if you want to figure
out what to do with the islands then you'll just use existing
ways of defining whether the islands are connected to the land or
not. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi
Meir omer now we get back to the משנה Mishnah which does
seem to be a more specifically related to the
תקנה. takana. רבי מאיר אומר עכו כארץ ישראל לגיטין. Rabbi Meir omer
Akko k'Eretz Yisrael le'Gittin. Akko counts like
Israel for for גיטין Gittin purposes. So only for גיטין Gittin purposes
not for other purposes, so that is a more tailored definition. בעי
מיניה רבי חייא בר אבא Ba'ei minei Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba they
asked רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba המוכר עבדו לסוריא
כמוכר בחוץ לארץ דמי או לא. hamocher avdo l'Suryia k'mocher bechul l'aretz
dami o lo.
What if somebody sells their slave to to סוריא, Surya, which is
like, you know, Syria? It's basically lands outside of Israel, the land
of Israel, that were conquered by דוד המלך. Dovid HaMelech. And the
question is as we'll see, does that have a status like the
land of Israel or not? Now, first of all, so this is
a concept called כיבוש יחיד. Kibush Yachid. It was conquered as an
individual conquering, not as a national conquering. We'll see what that means
in a minute. Okay. Also what's strange though is רש"י Rashi constantly
refers to what דוד המלך Dovid HaMelech did, but if we're in
בית שני Bayit Sheini times or post-בית שני Bayit Sheini times, it
should be more relevant about how that land was connected to Israel
in the time of בית שני, Bayit Sheini, not in בית ראשון,
Bayit Rishon, for תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot purposes. But there's a debate
throughout ש"ס Shas whether סוריא, Surya, these lands outside of Israel that
at one stage were connected to Israel, are they חייב chayiv in
תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot or not? So he wants to know, what
about for now not for גיטין, Gittin, that would be the immediate
case of us, but there's a third relevance for whether something is
Israel. There's a הלכה halacha which is if somebody sells their slave
outside of Israel, then the slave goes free because the slave is
obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot. They can't determine their own fate.
You're you know you're determining for them that they have to live
outside of Israel where is the center of a you know Jewish
community and opportunity to do מצוות. mitzvot. And therefore as a קנס
knas they said that the slave goes free. So he wants to
know what would happen if you sold your slave to סוריא. Surya.
Okay. כמוכר בחוץ לארץ דמי או לא? K'mocher b'chutz la'aretz dami o
lo? אמר ליה תניתוה, Amar lei tanituha, we taught it in our
משנה. mishna. רבי מאיר אומר עכו כארץ ישראל לגיטין. Rabbi Meir omer
Akko k'Eretz Yisrael l'Gittin. It's like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for גיטין.
Gittin. לגיטין אין לעבדים לא. L'Gittin in, l'avadim lo. Only for גיטין,
Gittin, meaning what's it coming to exclude? Well you could say it's
coming to exclude תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot purposes. But here it's understanding
that it's also excluding things that are similar to this מסכת, masechet,
meaning not זרעים Zeraim issues, but like Rabbinic תקנות takkanot about you
know in and out of Israel. So something similar to that is
this הלכה halacha of selling your slave. And therefore for slave purposes
it's considered out of Israel. So if עכו Akko is out of
Israel, even though it's right on the border, but because it's away
from the central you know sort of part of the land, כל
שכן סוריא דמרחקא טובה. kol sheken Surya d'merachaka tuva. How much more
so if you sell your slave to סוריא, Surya, very away from
the sort of central population, from you know that, how much more
so would the slave be considered selling to חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz.
So now what we have is three possible definitions. We have ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the purpose of תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot. We
have ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the purpose of גיטין, Gittin, right?
And we have ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the purpose of slaves.
All right. So are those is is the slave purpose and the
גיטין Gittin
definition the same? Not clear. But it's saying if something is considered
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz for גיטין, Gittin, here actually the גמרא Gemara
seems to be saying that it is considered the same. עכו Akko
is חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz for גיטין. Gittin. Okay. But he says
I'm sorry, no, no, it says it's not the same. עכו Akko
is חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz for גיטין. Gittin. I'm sorry. עכו Akko
is, one minute, המוכר... hamocher... hold on, hold on. עכו כארץ ישראל
לגיטין. Akko k'Eretz Yisrael l'Gittin.
Right. For רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, עכו Akko is like ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael for גיטין, Gittin, but for עבדים avadim it's not like
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the
definition for slaves we have is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is even
smaller. Again, presumably because it has to do with I don't know
where the major population is living and how you're disadvantaging the slave
from selling him away from you know where the major Jewish population
is living and so on. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that whatever
the land of Israel is for גיטין Gittin purposes, the definition for
slave purposes is potentially even smaller. All right. So we have three
definitions. We've got the תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot definition, we have the
גיטין Gittin definition which has to do with לשמה lishma and מצוי
לקיימו, matzui l'kaymo,
and we have the עבדים avadim definition of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
which has to do with what? It has to do with maybe
the חיוב במצוות, chiyuv b'mitzvot, but of course then that would be
the same as תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot u'Ma'asrot, you know if that's the
special מצווה mitzvah you're חייב chayav in. So probably has to do
with something like the עיקר יישוב ikkar yishuv of ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, where are the Jews living and where is it easy to
do מצוות. mitzvot. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says that if you've
got Israel here and if this is עכו, Akko, okay, and that's
considered ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for גיטין Gittin purposes, so that's for
גיטין Gittin purposes that is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but for slave
purposes that's somehow a, so the גיטין Gittin purposes is that definition,
but the slave definition is somehow assumed to be a little bit
smaller. Okay. So we don't know where, but let's say the slave
this is let's say the עבדים avadim is the עיקר יישוב ikkar
yishuv of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay, and the גיטין Gittin purposes
are let's say a little bit bigger, okay, because that's just where
people is they're travel, do they know לשמה, lishma, but that would
be even a little bit more at the periphery than where you
know the primary community is living. Okay. So we got three possible
definitions. So what it's saying is עכו Akko is like ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael for גיטין Gittin for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but for
slaves that would be considered חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. And certainly somewhere
out here, סוריא Surya would be considered maybe for תרומות ומעשרות Terumot
u'Ma'asrot it's חייב, chayiv, which we're going to see it is, but
certainly for גיטין Gittin and for עבדים avadim purposes that's חוץ לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. Okay. So we're going to see that it might be
that the
Because this has to be with practically where are people living? For
slaves whatever for that קנס, knas, you know, if you sell them
outside of the major centers, you're selling to חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
For גיטין, Gittin, okay, is there travel or not? But תרומות ומעשרות
Trumos U'Ma'asros may just be a more of a question of technically
what land was sanctified, even if the primary community is living further
away. So we're going to see that סוריא, Surya, I need a
third color, I think I have a third color.
What?
Let's see if I have to steal my- I got black.
Yeah, we'll use three colors. תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'Ma'asros and
this will be עבדים.
Avadim.
Okay, look at that.
Okay, so here, okay, סוריא, Surya,
what?
סוריא, Surya, this could be the land that is sanctified for תרומות
ומעשרות Trumos U'Ma'asros purposes, okay? Also includes nations out there, right? That
was land that was sanctified maybe in the time of דוד המלך,
David HaMelech, maybe it was land that was sanctified in the בית
שני, Bayis Sheini, but it doesn't mean that by the time the
משנה Mishnah is being written, that's where there's travel and לשמה, Lishma,
right? This is like לשמה Lishma and travel, right? This is probably
where it's like people are living,
okay, the and this is, you know, and this is land that
was sanctified. כיבוש יחיד? Kibush Yachid?
Well, we'll talk about it, we'll talk about it, but let's say
yes, okay? I mean, we'll see, but those are three different considerations.
So we were talking about do you go by some standard
pre-packaged definition which it seems like we were going about before when
we were talking about the rivers, okay, and here we're actually introducing
three different definitions based on different concerns. Okay? All right, so now
let's take a look. And we did it through סוריא, Surya, so
now we're going to look at סוריא. Surya. So let's take a
look. So certainly סוריא Surya that is more distant from the central
issue, notice by סוריא Surya it doesn't say whether it's sanctified or
not sanctified. You know, the question is, is it distant? Is it
distant from where most people are living? That clearly will give it
a status of חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz for the purposes of עבדים.
Avadim. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Aleppo, you said Aleppo?
רש"י, Rashi, Aleppo, where does it say Aleppo?
סוריא היא ארם צובא. Surya hee Aram Tzova. ארם צובא, Aram Tzova,
ah, okay. ארם צובא Aram Tzova is the major community.
Right, that's true. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
תנו רבנן בשלושה דרכים שוותה סוריא לארץ ישראל ובשלושה לחוצה לארץ. Tanu
Rabbanan bishlosha drachim shavsa Surya l'Eretz Yisrael u'bishlosha l'Chutz La'aretz.
Three ways it's similar to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and three ways
חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. עפרה טמא כחוצה לארץ. Afrah tamei k'Chutz La'aretz.
The dirt is טמא tamei for the הלכה halacha that there was
a, there's a double issue about what that's about. One is is
that there was a concern that outside of ישראל Yisrael the non-Jews
buried their dead in the ground, I mean not in the ground
but also like all over the place, without marking them, and therefore
for a כהן Kohen to go there they would become טמא, tamei,
but it also served a communal purpose of keeping people in ישראל,
Yisrael, particularly כהנים, Kohanim, but in general keeping people in ישראל, Yisrael,
so it was giving like real like הלכתי halachic reality to the
idea of like it's, you know, it's טמא tamei to live in
חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Like the holy place to live is ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and especially for כהנים. Kohanim. So anyway, they made
the dirt of חוץ לארץ טמא. Chutz La'aretz tamei. So for that,
סוריא Surya is כחוצה לארץ. k'Chutz La'aretz. והמוכר עבדו לסוריא כמוכר בחוצה
לארץ, V'hamocher avdo l'Surya k'mocher b'Chutz La'aretz, like we said before, if
you sell your slave it's like you're selling to חוץ לארץ. Chutz
La'aretz. והמביא גט מסוריא כמביא מחוצה לארץ. V'hameivi get mi'Surya k'meivi mi'Chutz
La'aretz. For גיטין Gittin purposes it's considered חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, right?
So for גיטין Gittin purposes you've only got this. For עבדים Avadim
but that is already is- that is not considered ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael for גט, Get, not for עבדים, Avadim, and we also say
עפרה טמא. afrah tamei. Okay, so we have עפרה טמא, afrah tamei,
but you would think if עפרה טמא afrah tamei it means that
it's totally חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. But let's keep on reading. Okay,
that's a third idea, עפרה טמא. afrah tamei. Then the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ובשלושה לארץ ישראל, u'bishlosha l'Eretz Yisrael, and three ways
it's like ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. חייבת במעשר ובשביעית כארץ ישראל. Chayaves
b'ma'aser u'bishvi'is k'Eretz Yisrael. It has קדושה kedusha of the ground. והרוצה
להיכנס לה בטהרה נכנס. V'harotzeh l'hikanes lah b'taharah nichnas. If you want
to go in and remain טהור, tahor, not encounter the dirt, the
טמא tamei dirt, there's a way to do it. We'll see about
that in a minute. והקונה שדה בסוריא כקונה
בפרורי ירושלים. V'hakoneh sadeh b'Surya k'koneh b'farvorei Yerushalayim. If you buy a
field in
סוריא Surya it's like buying in the center of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which
means if you're חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos U'Ma'asros, so we
want you to own fields there and the fields are going to
be חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos U'Ma'asros. And we're going to
see that we're going to encourage people to actually buy land in
סוריא, Surya, and we'll see what that means in a minute. So
this is very interesting, right? It's like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for
תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos U'Ma'asros, okay, but not for גיטין, Gittin, not for
עבדים. Avadim. It might have to do practically where people are living.
But we still want to like encourage people to purchase that land.
And even though it's חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, Trumos U'Ma'asros, we'll
still going to say עפרה טמא. afrah tamei. All right, so now
עפרה טמא afrah tamei might be a function, especially if it has
to do with where non-Jews are living. If that's why the dirt
is טמא, tamei, a) just you don't want people living where non-Jews
are living, b) because, you know, you don't want that they're burying
their dead all over the place. That might be more of a
function of these definitions which have to do with where people are
really living and not this which just has to do with whether
the land has been sanctified or not. Okay, so is that clear
that these two definitions are much more גיטין Gittin and עבדים avadim
practically where people live? This has to do with just more of
a question of was the land sanctified through some type of a
process and that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to turn to. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. It says like this.
It says
חייבת במעשר ובשביעית כארץ ישראל. chayavet b'maaser u'vshviis k'Eretz Yisroel. It's חייב
chayav in מעשר maaser and שביעית shviis like ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel.
Why? קסבר כיבוש יחיד שמו כיבוש. kasavar kibuish yachid shmo kibuish. That
conquering of an individual counts as conquering. Now what does that mean?
Very important debate throughout ש״ס Shas what that means. Look at רש״י.
Rashi. כיבוש יחיד. kibuish yachid. רש״י Rashi says כדוד. k'Dovid. The conquering
that דוד Dovid did. שלא היו כל ישראל ביחד כדרך שהיו בכיבוש
יהושע. shelo hayu kol Yisroel b'yachad k'derech shehayu b'kibuish Yehoshua. What makes
it not a standard conquering of a land that would sanctify it?
So רש״י Rashi says, well דוד Dovid was going off fighting his
own wars, he did not sort of have the country behind him.
So point number one for רש״י Rashi was it was not being
done together with the whole like as a national type of an
enterprise. Another רש״י Rashi says that he didn't have the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
to back him up. So you don't necessarily need your army to
be drafted from all twelve tribes, but you need to have like,
you know, congressional approval. You need to do something to make it
not your own little private war but something that makes it a
national enterprise. So רש״י Rashi is very much focusing on the יחיד.
yachid. It was דוד Dovid fighting some of his own wars, it
was not national enterprise. Also רש״י Rashi says וכיבושו לצורך כל ישראל
קודם חלוקה. v'kibusho l'tzorech kol Yisroel kodem chaluka. By יהושע Yehoshua not
only was it a national enterprise, it was done for the benefit
of כל ישראל Klal Yisroel to be divided. אבל דוד לא כבש
אלא לצורכו. aval Dovid lo kavash ela l'tzorcho. דוד Dovid did it
because he wanted it for his own purpose. Now it's funny how,
it wasn't his purpose as a private individual, it was his purpose
as a king, but it wasn't serving some obvious national purpose and
it wasn't being done as a national enterprise. Okay, and therefore, that
was conquered by a king, okay? Does that give it קדושה kedusha
if it was conquered as a king but not as part of
a national enterprise? And this position says yes, it does give it
קדושה kedusha for תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Okay. Now the funny thing
of course with that is, is that what does that, who cares?
הלכות halachos of תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros are based on what happened
in the time of the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. We say
the sanctity of יהושע Yehoshua does not continue to exist for תרומות
ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Okay. So that's just a question I want to
put out there, because what דוד Dovid did should not matter for
תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Nothing that happened in the first בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash should matter for contemporary תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. Anyway, look
back at תוספות Tosafos on דף ח׳. daf ches. כיבוש יחיד. kibuish
yachid. תוספות Tosafos has a different definition. תוספות Tosafos says the following.
פירש בקונטרס שלא היו לשם כל ישראל ביחד כמו בכיבוש יהושע וכיבושו
לצורך כולם ודוד לא כבש אלא לצורכו. peiraish b'kuntres shelo hayu l'sham
kol Yisroel b'yachad k'mo b'kibuish Yehoshua v'kibusho l'tzorech kulam v'Dovid lo kavash
ela l'tzorcho. אבל בספרי מפרש עניין אחר. aval b'Sifrei mefaraish inyan acher.
Another reason why it was problematic. בסוף פרשת ויהי עקב b'sof Parshas
v'haya eikev דמשמע דכל שלא הייתה עדיין כל ארץ ישראל כבושה d'mashma
d'chol shelo hayta adayin kol Eretz Yisroel kvusha that you cannot extend
the borders of Israel to make sort of annex land to the
borders of Israel for קדושה kedusha purposes only after the primary land
has been conquered. כדאיתא התם סמוך לפתור ידך שלא הורשת. k'deisa hatam
samuch l'pator yadcha shelo horashta. You didn't conquer near your own capital,
near your own castle. פירש יבוסי שהיה סמוך לירושלים. peiraish Yevusi shehaya
samuch l'Yerushalayim. You haven't conquered the יבוסי Yevusi near ירושלים Yerushalayim ואתה
הולך וכובש ארם נהריים וארם צובה? v'ata holech v'kovesh Aram Naharayim v'Aram
Tzova? And you're going to these other places? אבל אחר שכל ארץ
ישראל
כבושה aval achar shekol Eretz Yisroel kvusha after they conquered all of
Israel, דרש התם darash hatam כל מקום אשר תדרוך כף רגלכם לכם
kol makom asher tidroch kaf raglchem lachem שכל מה שהוא כובש חוצה
לארץ הרי הוא כקדוש ואפילו יחיד. shekol ma shehu kovesh chutz la'aretz
harei hu k'kadosh v'afilu yachid. So for תוספות Tosafos it did not
matter whether דוד Dovid was doing it as a private enterprise, what
mattered was whether you could incorporate it or annex it to the
primary land of Israel. And since it was conquered prior to the
primary land being fully conquered, it was not able to be incorporated,
or the question was, that's the question of כיבוש יחיד, kibuish yachid,
was it able to be incorporated into the primary land or not.
Okay, so we have this question about כיבוש יחיד kibuish yachid that
again what I do keep on pointing out because I just pointed
out so much because I don't see other people talking about it,
but to me it's an obvious problem, is who cares what דוד
המלך Dovid HaMelech did? תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros are supposed to follow
second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But anyway, for whatever reason, it was
conquered, it's not the primary land, it is these countries that have
been annexed or conquered. It's sanctified for תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, but
it ain't where the Jews are living. The Jews are living here,
okay? So for עבדים avadim purposes it's חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Right?
Here's another interesting question, right? Is this just תרומות ומעשרות? trumos u'maasros?
How about other מצוות mitzvos that depend specifically on the land of
Israel? Is it just that the dirt is sanctified, or is it
even conceptually considered, you know, to be the land of Israel, or
is it just no, it's sanctified with the קדושה kedusha of the
land? But anyway, the Jews are living here. So that's what's relevant
for גיטין Gittin and, you know, which is even broader, and עבדים
avadim which is even smaller. Okay, but here the Jews aren't living,
but the dirt is sanctified. So it's חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות,
trumos u'maasros, but because the Jews aren't living there, the dirt is
still טמא. tamei. Okay. So that's
what?
It's kind of a contrast,
that the dirt is טמא tamei and חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות.
trumos u'maasros. That's exactly where we're going to get to.
Right, so you could be חייב chayav *chayav* in תרומות *Trumos* and
מעשרות *Maisros*, you know, I mean it's funny, talk about it being
קדוש *kadosh*, you know, the sanctified dirt, and then we talk about
it being טמא tamei *tamei* because dead people are buried there. But
look, that's true even in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* too,
in a cemetery, if you were to plant in a cemetery, you'd
be חייב *chayav* in תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maisros* and it would
also be טמא *tamei*, you know? But it clearly points out, the
idea of the dirt being טמא *tamei* really does reflect this reality
of where the, you know, as a symbol that the, you know,
non-Jews live here, Jews don't live here, right? And that's what that's
about, yeah.
Even if they're not, well, two things. One is it's an irony
because the more קדוש *kadosh* something is, the more susceptibility to טומאה
*tumah*, right? So you have that interplay. But you're also suggesting, for
example, maybe they'd be חייב *chayav* in פאה *Pe'ah*?
Well, yes, but I'm thinking about like, yeah, I mean, the most
obvious things about ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael*, yeah, I was
talking
about things that are related to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* that are
not exactly about, you know, agriculture altogether.
קידוש החודש *Kiddush Hachodesh*?
Yeah, something like that, right. You know, I don't know when you
would talk about, you know, the people that would be חייב *chayav*
in, I mean, it's harder to find those things. But there are
some things, for the laws of קידוש החודש *Kiddush Hachodesh*, you know,
those type, I don't know. How about, how about שופטים ושוטרים תתן
לך בכל עריך בכל ארצך *Shoftim V'shotrim Titain Lecha Bechol Arecha Bechol
Artzecha*? How about עגלה ערופה *Egla Arufa*, would it apply in סוריא
*Surya*, you know? Presumably we're talking that it's not considered the Land
of Israel, just the sanctity, presumably. But those are interesting definitions to
play with. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, ורוצה *Varotze*, so now three lines from the top on ח
עמוד ב *chet amud beis*. ורוצה *Varotze* ליכנס *likaneis* לבטהרה *l'ba-tahara* נכנס
*nichnas*.
If you want to go in without becoming טמא *tamei*, that's possible.
ואמרת *Va'amarta* עפרא *afra* טמא *tamei*? Wait, wait, we said the dust
was טמא *tamei*. בשידה *Be'shida* תיבה *teiva* ומגדל *u'migdal*. No, you can
go in in a box. So, you know, talk about your Cat
in the Hat. So you go in, or not Cat in the
Hat, or what... anyway, your, your what was it, would you eat
it in a fox, would you eat it in a box? Okay,
so you're in a box.
Now, and that's protecting you from the dirt underneath. דתניא *De'tanya*, הנכנס
*ha'nichnas* לארץ העמים *l'eretz ha'amim* בשידה *be'shida* תיבה *teiva* ומגדל *u'migdal*,
in some type of a box, on a tower. רבי *Rebbe* מטמא
*metamei* ורבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *v'Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda* מטהר *metaher*.
רבי *Rebbe* says you're טמא *tamei*, so basically people are carrying you.
Here you are, you're in one of those, what are those things
called that were carried?
A palanquin?
Okay, a palanquin. Yeah, whatever, there you are, the dirt is down
there.
You drive in a car.
You drive in a car, right? These people are carrying you. Okay.
How about you're riding on a horse?
Exactly. Well תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says the same thing. Okay, fine. All
right, so they're carrying you. Okay, so are you protected from the
dirt? Because the dirt is מטמא *metamei*, but this is like an
אוהל *ohel*, so this protects you. So there's a way to go
in without becoming טמא *tamei*.
Yeah, but the guys you were touching are walking, they're טמא *tamei*.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, okay, so רבי *Rebbe*
says,
but רבי *Rebbe* says you're טמא *tamei* and רש"י Rashi: *Rashi* says
it's because of a principle of אוהל זרוק *ohel zaruk*, of like
an אוהל *ohel* that is moving, that's not stationary, that is not
חוצץ בפני הטומאה *chotetz bifnei hatuma*. Like the whole question about an
airplane, although that's also metal, so it's a different story. Anyway, so
for רבי *Rebbe* that doesn't work. רבי *Rebbe* מטמא *metamei* ורבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה *v'Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Yehuda* מטהר *metaher*. אפילו *Afilu* רבי
*Rebbe* לא קמטמא *lo ka'metamei* אלא *ela* בארץ העמים *b'eretz ha'amim* דגזרו
*d'gazru* גושה *gusha* ואוירה *ve'avira*. And even רבי *Rebbe*, he's only saying
it by normal חוץ לארץ chutz l'Aretz *Chutz La'aretz*, where not only
is it the dirt that's a problem, but the air's a problem.
אבל *Aval* סוריא *Surya*, but by סוריא *Surya*, על *al* גושה *gusha*
גזרו *gazru* אוירה *avira* לא גזרו *lo gazru*. Only on the dirt,
not on the air. And that's why סוריא *Surya* is more lenient.
In a normal חוץ לארץ chutz l'Aretz *Chutz La'aretz*, you would be
טמא *tamei* because of the air. Now, the air could just mean
that even if you're blocked from the dirt, we consider the very
air to be טמא *tamei*, so it doesn't help you. Or what
רש"י *Rashi* says, we could just mean by the air, is we
could mean not just touching the dirt, but even being over the
dirt. There's two conceptual different ways of thinking about it. Are we
literally saying the air is טמא *tamei*? Or just saying you can
become טמא *tamei* from the dirt if you're over it, even if
you don't touch it? But that's in normal חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*.
In סוריא *Surya*, we're a little bit more lenient. Only touching the
dirt is a problem, not the air, not being over the dirt.
So therefore everybody would agree in סוריא *Surya* you can go through
it with being טהור *tahor*. Okay? As long as you don't touch
the dirt in סוריא *Surya*, you're okay. All right? So that's number
two, the way it's like ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Not really like
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, but it's not as bad as the rest
of ארץ העמים *Eretz Ha'amim*. It sort of very nicely reflects its
middle type of position, or its multi-layered status. And number three is,
והקונה *ve'hakoneh* שדה *sade* בסוריא *b'Surya* כקונה *kekoneh* בפרורי *b'parvarei* ירושלים *Yerushalayim*.
If you buy a field in סוריא *Surya*, it's like you bought
in like the center of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. למאי *L'mai* הלכתא *hilchasa*? For
what purposes is that important, to purchase property there?
So, אמר רב ששת *amar Rav Sheshes*, לומר *lomar* שכותבין *shekosvin* עליו
*alav* אונו *ono* ואפילו *va'afilu* בשבת *b'Shabbos*. You can write the, you
can register it and you can write the bill of sale if
you're buying it from a non-Jew, because you want to have Jewish
possession of that territory, you can buy it, you can write it
up even on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
בשבת *b'Shabbos* סלקא דעתך *salka daitach*? What? בשבת סלקא דעתך? What, you
really can write on שבת, Shabbos. חילול שבת דאורייתא Chillul Shabbos d'Oraisa
still, right? Says גמרא, Gemara. all right, כדאמר רבא אומר לעכו"ם, ki
d'amar Rava omer l'Akum,
fine, fine, fine, you don't personally write on שבת. Shabbos. You have
a non-Jew draw up the documents on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, הכא נמי,
hacha nami, הכא נמי אומר לעכו"ם ועושה. hacha nami omer l'Akum v'oseh.
And here too, so the same way he says it over there,
by a place in Yerushalayim in ארץ ישראל proper, you can even
do that for this land, even though this land we just got
through saying is not really where the Jews are living. But nevertheless,
because it's חייב in תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, we want you to,
the better, more Jewish possession of that land the better. Now this
is quite ironic if you think about it. The reason we say
the dirt is טמא partly is to get you to not live
there. The reason that we say that if you sell your slave
in חוץ לארץ is like selling it to חוץ לארץ because that's
not where the Jews are living. But nevertheless, it's enough connected to
us that even if it's not the ideal place to live, and
even if it's not where the primary Jewish population is living, we
want to encourage you to purchase property there as long as, you
know, so and therefore we're going to let you actually get the
document signed, not for yourself to write it, but get the document
drawn up even on
שבת. Shabbos? Okay, ואף על גב דאמירה לעכו"ם שבות, v'af al gav
d'amira l'Akum shvus, even though having a non-Jew do something for you
is an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, משום יישוב ארץ ישראל לא גזרו
רבנן. mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael lo gazru rabanan. In order to settle
the land of Israel, the Rabbis weren't גוזר. gozer. So it's quite
strange, I'm very conflicted, I mean I love it because it's just
so, you know, complex and bizarre. It's called יישוב ארץ ישראל. yishuv
Eretz Yisrael. I mean, the עיקר יישוב ikar yishuv is over here.
Who's living off in Syria? Right? And by the way, you're buying
fields, you're not buying like, you know, fields means for planting, right?
Which connects to the תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. So it's one thing
to say you buy fields, תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, maybe it's saying,
who knows, maybe it's saying in order to provide food for people
living in Israel, we need to own like, you know, some nice,
wasn't it like Greece, primarily because I'm talking about, or not Greece,
Italy, like Sicily was the wheat fields for like, for Italy, is
that right? I think I remember from those Roman histories. Like that's
the way, anyway. So like maybe, like you know, if you buy
your fields here, you'll provide, it'll be nice to provide for, maybe
the יישוב ארץ ישראל yishuv Eretz Yisrael is the יישוב yishuv being
done over here by owning some fields out here. I don't know.
What?
Egypt was where all the Roman Empire. Oh, Egypt, I thought they
conquered Sicily for the wheat though, didn't they? I don't know. Anyway,
but it's quite interesting the concept of עפרא טמיא afra tmeia and
יישוב ארץ ישראל. yishuv Eretz Yisrael. You want to own land there.
But again, as I'm saying, it might be that you want to
own land there to provide for where the Jews are living in
Israel.
But if this is ממש להלכה, mamash l'halacha, forget Syria for a
moment. Let's go into the middle of ארץ ישראל. Right? Okay. Are
you telling me that for something that would be clearly justifiable מחמת
יישוב ארץ ישראל, machmas yishuv Eretz Yisrael, there's no שבות shvus on
שבת? Shabbos You can be מיקל? meikal?
I mean, possibly. I mean, here certainly for this. Yeah, I mean
quite possibly. Okay. I mean, in general we allow אמירה amira for
a non-Jew. There's even the position, part of this תוספות Tosafos is
a position of the ערוך Aruch that you allow אמירה amira to
a non-Jew on שבת for any מצווה mitzvah purpose. You allow אמירה
amira to a non-Jew. תוספות Tosafos says no, only for the מצווה
mitzvah of יישוב ארץ ישראל. yishuv Eretz Yisrael. For a different מצווה
mitzvah purpose, you would need two דרבנןs, d'rabbanan אמירה amira to a
non-Jew for a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but not אמירה amira for a non-Jew
for a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. But the ערוך Aruch actually learns from this
that אמירה amira to a non-Jew even for a דאורייתא d'Oraisa is
מותר muttar for all מצווה mitzvah purposes. But certainly for יישוב ארץ
ישראל yishuv Eretz Yisrael it seems like
מצווה mitzvah purpose including let's say עונג שבת oneg Shabbos to light
a fire?
Basically. I mean, for the ערוך. Aruch. We don't פוסקין pasken like
the ערוך, Aruch, although בשעת הדחק b'shaas hadchak sometimes some פוסקים, poskim,
like there's a רמ"א Rema that's prepared to rely on the ערוך
Aruch בשעת הדחק. b'shaas hadchak. But certainly for יישוב ארץ ישראל yishuv
Eretz Yisrael purposes, אמירה לגוי amira l'goy is basically מותר. muttar. That's
what the גמרא is saying.
You want us to rely on the ערוך?
Aruch? Who says that you can do an אמירה לגוי amira l'goy
on a דאורייתא d'Oraisa for צורך מצווה? tzorech mitzvah? Why not? The
ערוך Aruch was in the גאונים Geonim period. The רמ"א Rema is
a few hundred years later.
Not the ערוך השולחן, Aruch HaShulchan, the ערוך. Aruch. תוספות Tosafos, is
quoting the ערוך, Aruch, not the ערוך השולחן. Aruch HaShulchan. Okay. Nathan?
Yeah. From Rome. Exactly. Talking about Rome. Okay, fine. Let's take a
look at the first line of תוספות, might as well quote it.
Okay, he says: אף על גב דאמירה לעכו"ם שבות משום יישוב ארץ
ישראל לא גזרו רבנן אבל משום מצוה אחרת
לא היינו מתירים אמירה לעכו"ם במלאכה דאורייתא. Af al gav d'amira l'Akum
shvus, mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael lo gazru rabanan, aval mishum mitzvah acheres
lo hayinu matirim amira l'Akum be-melacha d'Oraisa. We would only allow an
אמירה amira for a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, not for a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. And
then he says, but then he quotes the ערוך Aruch and he
says like this: ומיהו בהלכות גדולות משמע דאפילו איסור דאורייתא שרי על
ידי עכו"ם לצורך מילה שפירש u'mihu be-Halachos Gedolos mashma d'afilu issur d'Oraisa
shari al yedei Akum l'tzorech milah she-pirash etc. etc.
Okay,
so there is this position in the גאונים Geonim that any
אמירה לגוי amira l'goy is מותר muttar for any מצווה. mitzvah. Okay,
but we generally פוסקין pasken only אמירה לגוי amira l'goy on a
דרבנן, d'rabbanan, not on a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa.
All right, back to the גמרא. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan: עבד שהביא
גיטו וכתוב בו עצמך ונכסיי קנויים לך עצמו קנה נכסים לא קנה.
Eved she-heivi gito v'kasuv bo atzmecha u'nechasai knuyim lach, atzmo kana nechasim
lo kana.
So since we introduced עבדים avadim into the discussion here, we're going
to talk about another funny הלכה halacha that's going to come up
in a משנה mishna which is... When an עבד eved brings a
when you deliver a גט, get, a גט get also means just
a document particularly also a instrument meaning not a document that's just
a שטר ראיה shtar raya just proving something happened, but it's actually
a document that is an instrument that effects a status change. So
one of the types of גט get is שחרור עבדים, shichrur avadim,
manumission of slaves. The גט get basically is the piece of paper
that says, you know, הרי אתה בן חורין, harei ata ben chorin,
הרי אתה לעצמך, harei ata l'atzmecha, similar idea, you're freeing the person.
Anyway, you give it to the עבד eved and the עבד eved
is freed. It causes a change of personal status. Let's say I
send my גט get for my עבד, eved, you know, and then
the שליח shaliach delivers it. Guess what the שליח shaliach has to
say when he delivers the גט get for the עבד? eved? בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם. b'fanai nechtav u'v'fanai nechtam. A similar תקנה. takana. So
now an עבד eved brought his own גט, get, okay, עבד שהביא
גיטו, eved she'heivi gitto, he brought his own גט get similar to
a woman bringing her own גט, get, okay, okay, so he says
it,
and he says, and it says on this גט, get, you and
my property are
given over to you. I'm giving you yourself and all of my
property. So עצמו קנה נכסים לא קנה. atzmo kanah nechasim lo kanah.
He owns himself but not the property. Why? Look at רש"י: עצמו
קנה דנאמן הוא על שחרורו לומר בפני נכתב ואין צריך עדים לקיימו.
atzmo kanah d'ne'eman hu al shichruro lomar b'fanai nechtav v'ein tzarich eidim
l'kaymo. So he's מקיים mekayeim the שטר. shtar. He says בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם. b'fanai nechtav u'v'fanai nechtam. That קיום kiyuum of the שטר,
shtar, right, because that his testimony works as a קיום, kiyuum, you
don't need two witnesses, that's a special leniency we give him here,
that works for the שחרור shichrur part of the שטר, shtar, what
makes this a special גט, get, which makes this the גט שחרור.
get shichrur. But נכסים לא קנה דבעי עדים כשאר קיומי שטרות. nechasim
lo kanah d'baei eidim k'sha'ar kiyumei shtaros. You have two things wrapped
up in one here. It's a gift document, there's no הלכה halacha
בפני נכתב b'fanai nechtav for a gift document. There's only הלכה halacha
בפני נכתב b'fanai nechtav for a גט אשה get isha and שחרור
עבדים. shichrur avadim. So this thing is two things wrapped up in
one, you got it? It's freeing the slave, and it's gifting him
the property. And he says בפני נכתב b'fanai nechtav on it. That
works for its status as a writ of manumission, as a גט
שחרור, get shichrur, and therefore he's validated the signatures from that perspective
and he's free. But if he wants to collect the property, he
has to treat it as a normal writ of a gift, and
he needs standard קיום שטרות, kiyuum shtaros, standard validation of signatures.
And then since this would be a gift from his master to
him who was manyu- whatever, freeing it.
איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they asked the question: כל נכסי קנויים לך.
kol nechasai k'nuim lach. Now let's say that's when there were two
statements in it: you and my property is transitioned to you. So
you could say there's two things here, it's a שטר shtar that's
doing two- it's two שטרות shtaros wrapped into one. But let's say
it's one one sentence, not two sentences. One sentence that means both.
All my property is given to you. So included in all my
property is yourself. Okay, same idea, but it's one sentence, it's not
two separate ideas in one package. Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha?
אמר אביי: amar Abaye: מתוך שקנה עצמו קנה נכסים. mitoch she'kanah atzmo
kanah nechasim.
Since the בפני נכתב b'fanai nechtav works for himself, it works for
the property. It's a קיום, kiyuum, it's all one שטר, shtar, it's
not two שטרות, shtaros, you know, even conceptually it's one statement, so
if the קיום kiyuum worked for part of it, it worked for
the whole statement. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, so Rava says
no. בשלמא עצמו לקני, bishlama atzmo liknei, he owns himself, מידי דהוה
אגט אשה, midi d'hava a'get isha, this idea of בפני נכתב b'fanai
nechtav it works for a like it works for a get of
for a get of divorce. אלא נכסים לא לקני, ela nechasim lo
liknei, but it shouldn't work for the for
to own the property, מידי דהוה אקיום שטרות דעלמא. midi d'hava a'kiyuum
shtaros d'alma.
Rava's like from that perspective it's a normal writ of a gift
and it would require normal validation of signatures, and בפני נכתב b'fanai
nechtav doesn't work. Which is basically Rava saying is I am not
impressed that it's doing two things in one sentence. It still works
from one perspective, the get part works, the normal מתנה matana part,
the קיום שטרות kiyuum shtaros does not work. הדר אמר אביי, hadar
amar Abaye, so Abaye did not want to give up on the
idea that it's all one package. So Abaye says fine, I'll say
it this way: מתוך שלא קנה נכסים לא קנה עצמו. mitoch she'lo
kanah nechasim lo kanah atzmo. Fine, you want- you don't like what
I said first, I'll try again, but I'm still not giving up
on the idea that it's one sentence. So if it doesn't work
for the מתנה matana part, the בפני נכתב, b'fanai nechtav, it doesn't
work for the get part. But I'm still insisting it's all one
thing. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, Rava of course refuses to
hear this. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, Rava says back to
him: בשלמא נכסים לא לקני, bishlama nechasim lo liknei, no, I agree
with you you don't own the property, because מידי דהוה אקיום שטרות
דעלמא, midi d'hava a'kiyuum shtaros d'alma, because it's just it's because to
treat it as a gift document, it needs normal validation, so I
get it doesn't work to validate the signatures from its perspective as
a gift document. אלא עצמו לקני, ela atzmo liknei, but let him
free himself, מידי דהוה אגט אשה, midi d'hava a'get isha, but it
still should be looked at as from the perspective of a, you
know, of a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. And it should work. So
basically, it's so funny, like they're not hearing each other. They're talking,
you know, they're talking like parallel to each other. רבא's Rava saying
I'm willing to look at it in two dimensions and say the
קיום kiyum works for the גט שחרור get shichrur part and it
doesn't work for the מתנה matana part. אביי Abaye says it's all
one sentence. So either it's going to work for both or it's
not going to work for both, but you can't have, you can
say the קיום kiyum works for that line and not for that
line, but if it's all one line, it's all the same words,
it either works for that sentence or it doesn't work for that
sentence. You can't split the effects of that sentence. Okay, so that's
a debate, and we'll just read רבא's Rava position. אלא אמר רבא,
Ela amar Rava, it's very clear where רבא's Rava going, אחד זה
ואחד זה, echad zeh ve-echad zeh, whether it is phrased as two
sentences or as one sentence, עצמו קנה נכסים לא קנה. atzmo kanah
nechasim lo kanah. It works for himself, but even if it's just
one sentence, the קיום kiyum works for the part of it that
refers to freeing the slave, that is a good קיום. kiyum. For
נכסים, nechasim, the part of it that is a gift document even
if it's the exact same sentence, לא קנה, lo kanah, it does
not work. So for אביי Abaye you can split the קיום kiyum
between—excuse me, for רבא Rava you can split the קיום kiyum if
they're two
separate phrases—yeah, for אביי Abaye you can split the קיום kiyum if
they're two separate phrases; the קיום kiyum works for this phrase, not
that phrase. But if it's one phrase, it's either a קיום kiyum
for the whole phrase and in both of its ramifications or for
neither of its ramifications. But you have to do what's the physical
phrase, it either works for it or it doesn't. And רבא's Rava
willing to split the effect. Even though it's one phrase, for the
degree that the phrase is working to free him, it works; for
the degree that the phrase is giving him a gift, it does
not work. Okay, and we'll unpack this tomorrow.
We said they had...